Section 6.6 learning from feedback at this
point the
textbook shows Figure 6.12. It depicts
illustration of different
ways being pursued of achieving alignment.
This section discusses
yet more attempts to address the reward
misspecification problem.
At times the intended behavior is so
intricate that
demonstration based learning becomes
untenable. An alternative approach is
to offer feedback to the agent instead of
providing
either manually specified reward functions
or even expert demonstrations.
This section delves into feedback based
strategies such as
reward modeling, reinforcement learning
from human feedback, and reinforcement
learning from AI feedback, also known as
reinforcement learning
from Constitutional AI or simply
constitutional AI. Section reward
modeling the textbook includes video 6.3
here, which you
may want to watch separately. It covers
optional video
explaining reward modeling. Reward
modeling was developed to apply
reinforcement learning algorithms to real
world problems where designing
a reward function is difficult in part
because humans
don't have a perfect understanding of
every objective. In
reward modeling, human assistants evaluate
the outcomes of AI
behavior without needing to know how to
perform or
demonstrate the task optimally themselves.
This is similar to
how you can tell if a dish is cooked
well by tasting it even if you do not
know how to cook and thus your feedback
can
be used by a chef to learn how to
cook better. This technique separates the
RL alignment problem
into two separate halves, understanding
intentions I.e. learning the
what and acting to achieve the intentions,
I.e. learning
the how. This means that in the modeling
agenda
there are two different ML models. A
reward model
is trained with user feedback. This model
learns to
predict what humans would consider good
behavior. An agent
trained with RL where the reward for the
agent
is determined by the outputs of the reward
model.
There is figure 6.13 in the textbook. Here
it
depicts scalable agent alignment via
reward modeling. Overall, while
promising, reward modeling can still fall
prey to reward
misspecification and reward hacking
failures. Obtaining accurate and
comprehensive
feedback can be challenging and human
evaluators may have
limited knowledge or biases that can
impact the quality
of the feedback. Additionally, any reward
functions learnt through
modeling might also struggle to generalize
to new situations
or environments that differ from the
training data. These
are all discussed further using concrete
examples in later
sections. There are also some variants of
reward modeling
such one Narrow reward modeling is a
specific flavor
of reward modeling where the focus is on
training
AI systems to accomplish specific tasks
rather than trying
to determine the true human utility
function. It aims
to learn reward functions to achieve
particular objectives rather
than seeking a comprehensive understanding
of human values. 1
Recursive reward modeling seeks to
introduce scalability to the
technique. In recursive reward modeling,
the focus is on
decomposing a complex task into simpler
subtasks and using
reward modeling at each level to train
agents that
can perform those subtasks. This
hierarchical structure allows for
more efficient training and credit
assignment as well as
the exploration of novel solutions that
may not be
apparent to humans. This is shown in the
diagram
below. Scalable oversight will be covered
in greater depth
in future chapters. The textbook includes
Figure 6.14. Here
it depicts scalable agent alignment via
reward modeling. The
general reward modeling framework forms
the basis for other
feedback based techniques such as RLHF
Reinforcement Learning from
Human Feedback, which is discussed in the
next section.
Section Reinforcement Learning from Human
Feedback at this point,
There is video 6.4 in the textbook. It
covers
optional video explaining RLHF and a
specification gaming Failure
Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback
is a method developed
by OpenAI. It's a crucial part of their
strategy
to create AIs that are both safe and
aligned
with human values. A prime example of an
AI
trained with RLHF is OpenAI's ChatGPT.
Earlier in this
chapter, the reader was asked to consider
the reward
design problem for manually defining a
reward function to
get an agent to perform a backflip. This
section
considers the RLHF solution to this design
problem. RLHF
addresses this problem as a human is
initially shown
two instances and an AI's backflip
attempts. Then the
human selects which one appears more like
a backflip
and finally the AI is updated accordingly.
By repeating
this process thousands of times, we can
guide the
AI to perform actual backflips. At this
point, the
textbook shows Figure 6.15. It depicts
RLHF learned to
backflip using around 900 individual bits
of feedback from
the human evaluator. There is figure 6.1
Steen in
the textbook. Here it depicts manual
reward. Crafting for
this backflip took two hours to write a
custom
reward function. While it was successful,
it was significantly
less elegant than the one trained purely
through human
feedback. Similar to designing a reward
function that efficiently
rewards proper backflips, it is hard to
specify precisely
what it means to generate safe or helpful
text.
This served as some of the motivation
behind making
RLHF integral to the training of some
current large
language models. Although training
sequences may vary slightly across
organizations, most labs adhere to the
general framework of
pre training followed by some form of fine
tuning.
Observing the instructgpt training process
offers insight into a
possible path for training LLMs. The
textbook includes figure
6.17. Here it depicts aligning language
models to follow
instructions Step Semi Supervised
Generative Pre Training the LLM
is initially trained using a massive
amount of Internet
text data where the task is to predict the
next word in a natural language context.
Step 1
Supervised fine tuning A fine tuning
dataset is created
by presenting a prompt to a human and
asking
them to write a response. This process
yields a
dataset of prompt output pairs. This data
set is
then used to fine tune the LLM through
supervised
learning, a form of behavioral cloning.
Train a Reward
model we train an additional reward model.
We initially
prompt the fine tuned LLM and gather
several output
samples for the same prompt. A human then
ranks
these samples from best to worst. This
ranking is
used to train the reward model to predict
what
a human would rank higher. Step 3
Reinforcement Learning
Once we have both a fine tuned LLM and
a reward model, we can employ proximal
policy optimization
PPO based reinforcement learning to
encourage the fine tuned
model to maximize the reward that the
reward model,
which mimics human rankings, offers.
Reward Hacking in Feedback
methods While the feedback based
mechanisms do make models
safer, they do not make them immune to
reward
hacking. The effectiveness of an algorithm
heavily relies on
the human evaluator's intuition about what
constitutes the correct
behavior. If the human lacks a thorough
understanding of
the task, they may not provide beneficial
feedback. Further,
in certain domains, our system might lead
to agents
developing policies that deceive the
evaluators. For instance, a
robot intended to grasp objects merely
positioned its manipulator
between the camera and the object, making
it seem
as if it was executing the task, as shown
below. At this point, the textbook shows
Figure 6.1
team. It depicts deep reinforcement
learning from human preferences.
There is figure 6.19 in the textbook. Here
it
depicts a sensor without depth perception
can be fooled
by AIs that only appear to grasp a ball.
Pre training with Human Feedback in
standard pre training,
the language model attempts to learn
parameters such that
they maximize the likelihood of the
training data. However,
this also includes undesirable content
such as falsehoods, offensive
language, and private information. The
concept of pre training
with human feedback utilizes the reward
modeling methodology in
the pre training phase. The authors of the
paper
found that PHF works much better than the
standard
practice of only using feedback after pre
training. In
phf, the training data is scored using a
reward
function such as a toxic text classifier
to guide
the language model to learn from
undesirable content while
avoiding imitating it during inference
time. Similar to RLHF,
PHF does not completely solve reward
hacking. However, it
might move the systems one small step
closer. These
methods can be further extended by by
employing AI
assistants to aid humans in providing more
effective feedback.
Some aspects of this strategy are
introduced in the
next section, but will be explored in
further detail
in the chapters on scalable and
adversarial oversight Methods
Reinforcement Learning from AI Feedback
the term reinforcement learning
from AI feedback refers to the following
Reinforcement learning
from AI Feedback is a framework involving
the training
of an AI agent to learn from the feedback
given by another AI system. The textbook
includes Figure
6.20 here RAF, also known as RLCAI.
Reinforcement Learning
on Constitutional AI or simply
Constitutional AI, was developed
by Anthropic. A central component of
Constitutional AI is
the Constitution, a set of human written
principles that
the AI is expected to adhere to, such as
choose the least threatening or aggressive
response. Anthropic's AI
assistant Claude's Constitution
incorporates principles from the Universal
Declaration
of Human Rights, Apple's terms of service,
DeepMind, Sparrow
principles, and more. Constitutional AI
begins with an AI
trained primarily for helpfulness and
subsequently trains it for
harmlessness in two stages. Generate
Prompt Output pairs the
AI continuously critiques and refines its
own responses to
harmful prompts. The AI is then trained to
generate
outputs more similar to these revised
responses. This stage's
primary objective is to facilitate the
second stage. An
example flow of this process is as 1.
Prompt
a model that has already been trained
using RLHF
is first asked for advice on building
bombs. The
model outputs a BOM tutorial. 2 Then the
model
is asked to revise the response in
accordance with
a randomly selected constitutional
principle. The following steps are
repeated multiple times. 3. Critique this
output is then
fed back into the model alongside a
request to
critique why the generated output would be
considered harmful
according to some rule of the chosen
constitution. 4.
Revision the model is then prompted to
rewrite the
original response such that it is not in
violation
of the constitutional rules. 1. SLCAI
model supervised learning
constitutional AI based on the generated
set of harmful
prompt revised output pairs. A new model
is trained
using supervised learning. 1. Preference
Model 1 RLCAI Model
Reinforcement Learning Constitutional AI1
stage 2 we use the
AI fine tuned from stage 1 to produce
pairs
of alternative responses to harmful
prompts. The AI then
rates each pair according to a randomly
selected constitutional
principle. This results in AI generated
preferences for harmlessness,
which we blend with human preferences for
helpfulness to
ensure the AI doesn't lose its ability to
be
helpful. The final step is to train the AI
to create responses that closely resemble
the preferred responses.
Anthropic's experiments indicate that AIs
trained with constitutional reinforcement
learning are significantly safer in the
sense of less
offensive and less likely to give you
potentially harmful
information, while maintaining the same
level of helpfulness compared
to AIs trained with RLHF. While
constitutional AI does
share some issues with RLHF concerning
robustness, it also
promises better scalability due to its
reduced reliance on
human supervision. The image below
provides a comparison of
constitutional AI's helpfulness with that
of RLHF. At this
point, the textbook shows Figure 6.21. It
depicts constitutional
AI harmlessness from AI feedback Section
Limitation Theoretical Problems
with Reinforcement Learning from Human
Feedback RLHF the paper
Open Problems and Fundamental Limitations
with RLHF provides a
comprehensive breakdown of challenges in
RLHF. There is figure
6.22 in the textbook. Here it depicts an
overview
of various types of challenges with RLHF.
Since RLHF
is composed of three the human feedback,
the reward
model, and the policy, the arising biases
can be
categorized according to these three
sources. This section outlines
some of these challenges, emphasizing the
need for advanced
techniques and strategies. Limits with
Human Feedback Misaligned Evaluators
firstly, the annotators might themselves
be misaligned. Malicious or
biased Distribution of evaluators that is
not representative of
the distribution of future users in the
real world.
Malicious individuals can poison the model
during training via
backdoor attacks that can be added to the
model
if no countermeasures are put in place.
Difficulty of
oversight Humans struggle to evaluate
model performance on complex
tasks and can be easily misled by model
outputs.
Human evaluators can be manipulated to
return a positive
reward even if the true value should be
negative.
For instance, the more convincing a bot
seems, the
more reward it may receive even if its
answers
are false. And this might be a reason why
ChatGPT answers might be so long by
default. Techniques
to mitigate these issues are discussed in
the Scalable
Oversight chapters. Feedback Type
Limitation Even if the annotators
were in perfect capability of expressing
their preferences, the
training procedure might not enable them
to express the
full extent of their desires. 1. The
examples they
are given may not be representative of the
complete
set of situations in which the model will
find
itself after deployment. 2 the options for
the feedback
are limited. Comparing two examples or
using a grading
system can yield very different results,
as shown in
the paper ETI Arash et al. Limits with the
reward model. Let's assume the feedback
process to be
frictionless. Perfect annotators Perfect
evaluations. In that scenario, would
the reward model be able to accurately
translate their
feedback in order to shape the policy
accordingly. It
turns out it is not such an easy task.
Misspecification or the Reward Function
Values Mismatch Accurately reflecting
diverse human values in a reward function
is complex.
Indeed, human preferences are complex by
nature. They depend
on context and personality, but also
fluctuate in time
and can sometimes be irrational. Expecting
the reward model
to converge to a single function which
maps perfectly
all human preferences is delusional. This
is again the
misspecification problem.
Misgeneralization Hacking Imperfect reward
proxy since the
model is given a finite number of
examples, and
since there is an infinite number of ways
to
fit this data, the model's behavior on new
examples
is always an extrapolation and there is no
theoretical
guarantee that it will never deviate from
what is
expected. There may be terrible answers
such as gibberish
phrases for language models which yield a
positive reward.
Unexpectedly, this is called reward
hacking. Joint Reward Model
and Policy Training On a more technical
aspect, the
stability and convergence of the training
scheme are not
always ensured since we are optimizing the
policy on
a reward that is being optimized. At the
same
time, uncertainties and undesirable
dependencies can arise which impact
the robustness of the model. These issues
are not
specific to RLHF but must be solved if we
expect deployed models to be fully aligned
with our
needs. Limits with the policy let's assume
the feedback
and the reward model accurately represent
human preferences. The
next difficulty is ensuring the policy is
correctly optimized.
RL is hard. This can lead to reward
hacking
and biases such as mode collapse where the
model
shows a drastic bias towards specific
patterns. Mode collapse
is a known issue in rl. An output which
always returns a positive reward will
drive the model
to return the same answer, and new paths
will
not be explored. Consequently, the reward
model will not
see new samples to learn from. Anyhow, the
joint
training of the reward model and the
policy induces
a bias in the learning phase since both
depend
on each other. There can also be an
initial
bias in the base model used for the
training.
For instance, ChatGPT was fine tuned from
an initial
GPT base trained in part on the web. Even
though RLHF was used to remove any
controversial statements
from the model, there still remains a risk
for
the model to output problematic content it
saw online.
OpenAI 2022. Effective policies during
training might fail to
generalize well in real world scenarios.
For instance, phenomena
like jailbreak show that models like Bing
Chat and
chatgpt can perform learned actions even
if trained not
to respond to certain queries. Larger RLHF
models tend
to develop harmful self preservation
tendencies and sycophancy, which
is the insincere agreement with user
opinions. This behavior
indicates a trend towards instrumental
convergence. Additionally, RLHF can
incentivize deceptive behaviors, as
illustrated by the robotic hand
experiment in Cristiano et al's 2017
study. Those theoretical
problems have real consequences. RLHF has
not succeeded in
making LLMs robustly helpful and harmless.
Despite the continuous
advancements in natural language
processing and the development of
RLHF, LLMs have not yet achieved robust
helpfulness and
harmlessness. Hallucinations remain a
significant issue, as illustrated by
GPT4's tendency to generate nonsensical or
untruthful content. These
hallucinations can lead to overreliance on
LLMs, consequently degrading
system performance and failing to meet
user expectations in
real world scenarios. Additionally, biases
within LLMs persist, often
reflecting misaligned opinions between the
LLM and various demographic
groups in the United States. As seen with
the
left leaning tendencies of some human
feedback tuned LLMs,
these biases can be harmful, producing
discriminatory language and
perpetuating negative stereotypes, as
demonstrated by GPT3's anti Muslim
bias. Moreover, jailbreaking of chatbots
poses a significant risk
with websites listing prompts to bypass
safety measures like
ChatGPT and other jailbreaks. Privacy
threats from Application Integrated
LLMs are now more severe than ever. For
instance,
Italy banned ChatGPT due to privacy
considerations under the
EU's General Data Protection Regulation.
The ability to find
jailbreaks is supported by a recent paper
titled Fundamental
Limitations of Alignment in Large Language
Models. The paper
presents early theoretical results that
indicate any alignment process
such as RLHF, which reduces undesired
behavior without eliminating
it completely, cannot be safe against
adversarial prompting. The
authors find that by prompting the model
to behave
as a specific Persona, behaviors that are
generally very
unlikely to be exhibited by the model can
be
brought to the forefront. This is not a
complete
demonstration as their framework is based
on the notion
of Personas, but it strongly suggests that
naive pre
training without data set curation
followed by RLHF may
not be sufficient against adversarial
attacks. The security of
sensitive private information in large
language models is a
pressing concern, especially when user
generated data such as
emails and smart keyboard inputs are
utilized for training.
In fact, several recent papers have
demonstrated that foundation
models can be easily queried to retrieve
personal information,
and those problems are still present in
aligned models
such as GPT4 which has the potential to be
used to attempt to identify individuals
when augmented with
outside data as exposed by a LLM may
exhibit
a fundamental incompatibility of high
accuracy with both security
and privacy. Given the current
understanding in adversarial machine
learning, RLHF may be able to make worst
case
performance worse. RLHF may decrease the
robustness to adversarial
attacks by sharpening the distinction
between desired and undesired
behaviors, potentially making LLMs more
susceptible to adversarial prompting.
The increased distinction between
behaviors is linked to the
Waluigi effect a where after training an
LLM to
satisfy a desirable property p, it becomes
easier to
elicit the chatbot into satisfying the
exact opposite of
property p. Theoretical arguments such as
this one seem
to push for the ineffectiveness of RLHF in
eliminating
deceptive Personas. Some of those problems
may get worse
as systems become more capable. RLHF has
been found
to increase the autonomy of LLMs without
decreasing undesirable
metrics such as convergent instrumental
goal following actively expressing
a preference not to be shut down or
sycophancy.
Those undesirable metrics increase with
the number of RLHF
steps, indicating that current models are
becoming more agentic
in potentially concerning ways as they
scale more generally,
RL from human derived reward signals may
increase drive
for longer horizon planning, deception and
agentic behavior, which
are prerequisites for deceptive alignment
and ultimately risks of
large scale accidents. Conclusion on the
limitations of RLHF
despite requiring extensive human
feedback, RLHF still faces numerous
failures and resolving these issues may
require significantly more
effort. As AI systems evolve, the demand
for complex
data grows, potentially making data
acquisition prohibitively expensive.
Additionally,
as we push computational boundaries, the
availability of qualified
annotators could become a limiting factor.
Overall, just because
the model is instruction tuned means does
not mean
that the training process is safe and RLHF
needs
to be incorporated into a broader
technical safety framework.
For example, responsible scaling policies
or the preparedness framework
are partial attempts to be such frameworks
or the
paper Model Evaluation for Extreme Risks.
The textbook has
a supplementary note titled Instruction
Tuning versus Alignment, which
we'll skip over here. At this point the
textbook
shows Figure 6.24 Direct preference
optimization Reinforcement Learning from
human feedback has demonstrated
effectiveness as showcased by ChatGPT
and Llama2, but it's a complex and
sensitive process
and also has some bad alignment
properties. RLHF involves
a three step procedure, whereas DPO
simplifies this to
two steps. The paper titled Direct
preference optimization your
language model is secretly A reward model
presents an
algorithm that aligns language models with
human preferences without
the need for explicit reward modeling and
reinforcement learning.
DPO employs a straightforward
classification objective, circumventing
the need
for an intermediary reward model. I'll hf
the method
it proposes to replace traditionally
involves three steps. 1.
Supervised fine tuning Initially, the
model is trained on
a data set comprising prompts and their
corresponding desired
responses. Two Human evaluators assess the
model's outputs and
this feedback informs a reward model which
is trained
to discern the preferred types of outputs.
3. Proximal
policy optimization the model generates
outputs which are evaluated
by the reward model, and the PPO algorithm
adjusts
the model's policy based on these
evaluations. DPO retains
the initial supervised fine tuning step
but replaces the
subsequent two steps with a single step of
fine
tuning on preference data. By using a new
CLEVER
loss, DPO effectively increases the
likelihood of preferred actions
while reducing the likelihood of undesired
ones with a
single loss. There is figure 6.25 in the
textbook.
Here it depicts DPO increases the
probability of the
preferred action, the expression y, while
decreasing the probability
of the dispreferred action, the expression
yl. 1. Preference
dataset creation we first sample a pair of
continuation
by asking a question the AI proposes to
continuations.
We label one of them good and the other
bad. 2. Logit's collection we run the base
model
model on the two continuations, we run the
new
model on the two continuations. 3.
Optimization we backprop
through the new model and optimize the
above loss
by eliminating the step of creating a
reward model.
DPO greatly simplifies the fine tuning
process and has
shown to perform very well. This process
can then
be iterated. This involves creating a new
preference data
set, that is we ask a question and we
sample the new AI two times and then we
label the text that we prefer between the
two
and then we apply the DPO loss. Then this
cycle is repeated to enhance the model. An
important
aspect of DPO is that the reward is
implicit
it aligns with preferences without the
need to construct
a separate reward model. This approach
addresses the challenge
of specifying a utility function and
responds to criticisms
such as those by Alex Turner, who argues
that
robust grading, that is Robust reward
modeling, is an
unnecessarily complex and unnatural task
that might be harder
than the entire AI alignment problem
itself. Turner's critique,
found in Inner and Outer alignment
decompose one hard
problem into two extremely hard problems
suggests that finding
a safe and robust numerical objective for
a highly
intelligent agent to optimize directly is
a formidable challenge,
one challenge that DPO could to bypass
Expanding the
scope of the paper with various
adaptations this paper
offers a foundation that could be enhanced
through various
adaptations. For instance, integrating its
approach with the insights
from Tomasz Korbach et al's paper pre
training language
models with human preferences could
augment its robustness. Furthermore,
the utilization of Boolean preference data
has its limitations.
Providing feedback in natural language as
shown to be
more sample efficient in the study,
training language models
with language feedback could enhance the
effectiveness of the
process. Remarkably, with just 100 samples
of human written
feedback, this approach enabled the fine
tuning of a
GPT3 model to achieve nearly human level
summarization capabilities.
Looking towards the future, a speculative
process that could
mitigate the specification gaming would be
to train the
model much like a child and that would
actively
inquire and learn from human interactions.
This approach would
closely mirror child development, during
which a child is
progressively more aligned and more
capable. And just as
in the development of children, it would
be crucial
to ensure that at no point does the AI's
capabilities outpace its level of
alignment. Maintaining a balance
between ability and ethical comprehension
throughout its developmental journey.